<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Climate and Societal Analytics</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Climate and Societal Analytics</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Climate and Societal Analytics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New study on heat-related mortality in Germany</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/news/2024-10-21-heat-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/news/2024-10-21-heat-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our PhD student Junyu published his work on heat-related mortality in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s43856-024-00643-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nature Communications Medicine&lt;/a&gt;. This work complements the ongoing efforts of RKI to understand and monitor climate-driven public health effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the abstract:&lt;br&gt;
Heat has become a leading cause of preventable deaths during summer. Understanding the link between high temperatures and excess mortality is crucial for designing effective prevention and adaptation plans. Yet, data analyses are challenging due to often fragmented data archives over different agglomeration levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Germany as a case study, we develop a multi-scale machine learning model to estimate heat-related mortality with variable temporal and spatial resolution. This approach allows us to estimate heat-related mortality at different scales, such as regional heat risk during a specific heatwave, annual and nationwide heat risk, or future heat risk under climate change scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High-resolution modeling and projection of heat-related mortality in Germany under climate change</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/wang-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/wang-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Publication in Giga Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/news/2024-08-08-giga-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/news/2024-08-08-giga-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our PhD student Eva published her first-author paper &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article/doi/10.1093/gigascience/giae051/7730001&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Impact of reference design on estimating SARS-CoV-2 lineage abundances from wastewater sequencing data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in Giga Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study highlights current computational challenges, focusing on the general reference design, which directly impacts abundance allocations. The authors illustrate advantages and disadvantages that may be relevant for further developments in the wastewater community and in the context of defining robust quality metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
Sequencing of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) RNA from wastewater samples has emerged as a valuable tool for detecting the presence and relative abundances of SARS-CoV-2 variants in a community. By analyzing the viral genetic material present in wastewater, researchers and public health authorities can gain early insights into the spread of virus lineages and emerging mutations. Constructing reference datasets from known SARS-CoV-2 lineages and their mutation profiles has become state-of-the-art for assigning viral lineages and their relative abundances from wastewater sequencing data. However, selecting reference sequences or mutations directly affects the predictive power.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>WASSA @ ACL 2024 Paper accepted!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/news/2024-08-07-wassa-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/news/2024-08-07-wassa-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our paper &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aclanthology.org/2024.wassa-1.13/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Guiding Sentiment Analysis with Hierarchical Text Clustering: Analyzing the German X/Twitter Discourse on Face Masks in the 2020 COVID-19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is accepted at the 14th Workshop on Computational Approaches to Subjectivity, Sentiment &amp;amp; Social Media Analysis (WASSA), which takes place at the ACL 2024 conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt; Social media are a critical component of the information ecosystem during public health crises. Understanding the public discourse is essential for effective communication and misinformation mitigation. Computational methods can aid these efforts through online social listening. We combined hierarchical text clus- tering and sentiment analysis to examine the face mask-wearing discourse in Germany during the COVID-19 pandemic using a dataset of 353,420 German X (formerly Twitter) posts from 2020. For sentiment analysis, we annotated a subsample of the data to train a neural network for classifying the sentiments of posts (neutral, negative, or positive). In combination with clustering, this approach uncovered sentiment patterns of different topics and their subtopics, reflecting the online public response to mask mandates in Germany. We show that our approach can be used to examine long-term narratives and sentiment dynamics and to identify specific topics that explain peaks of interest in the social media discourse.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guiding Sentiment Analysis with Hierarchical Text Clustering: Analyzing the German X/Twitter Discourse on Face Masks in the 2020 COVID-19 Pandemic</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/conference-paper/wehrli-etal-2024-guiding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/conference-paper/wehrli-etal-2024-guiding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social media are a critical component of the information ecosystem during
public health crises. Understanding the public discourse is essential for effective
communication and misinformation mitigation. Computational methods can aid these
efforts through online social listening. We combined hierarchical text clustering
and sentiment analysis to examine the face mask-wearing discourse in Germany during
the COVID-19 pandemic using a dataset of 353,420 German X (formerly Twitter) posts
from 2020. For sentiment analysis, we annotated a subsample of the data to train
a neural network for classifying the sentiments of posts (neutral, negative, or
positive). In combination with clustering, this approach uncovered sentiment patterns
of different topics and their subtopics, reflecting the online public response to
mask mandates in Germany. We show that our approach can be used to examine long-term
narratives and sentiment dynamics and to identify specific topics that explain peaks
of interest in the social media discourse.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impact of reference design on estimating SARS-CoV-2 lineage abundances from wastewater sequencing data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/10-1093-gigasciencegiae-051/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/10-1093-gigasciencegiae-051/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sequencing of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2)
RNA from wastewater samples has emerged as a valuable tool for detecting the presence
and relative abundances of SARS-CoV-2 variants in a community. By analyzing the
viral genetic material present in wastewater, researchers and public health authorities
can gain early insights into the spread of virus lineages and emerging mutations.
Constructing reference datasets from known SARS-CoV-2 lineages and their mutation
profiles has become state-of-the-art for assigning viral lineages and their relative
abundances from wastewater sequencing data. However, selecting reference sequences
or mutations directly affects the predictive power.Here, we show the impact of a
mutation- and sequence-based reference reconstruction for SARS-CoV-2 abundance estimation.
We benchmark 3 datasets: (i) synthetic “spike-in”’ mixtures; (ii) German wastewater
samples from early 2021, mainly comprising Alpha; and (iii) samples obtained from
wastewater at an international airport in Germany from the end of 2021, including
first signals of Omicron. The 2 approaches differ in sublineage detection, with
the marker mutation-based method, in particular, being challenged by the increasing
number of mutations and lineages. However, the estimations of both approaches depend
on selecting representative references and optimized parameter settings. By performing
parameter escalation experiments, we demonstrate the effects of reference size and
alternative allele frequency cutoffs for abundance estimation. We show how different
parameter settings can lead to different results for our test datasets and illustrate
the effects of virus lineage composition of wastewater samples and references.Our
study highlights current computational challenges, focusing on the general reference
design, which directly impacts abundance allocations. We illustrate advantages and
disadvantages that may be relevant for further developments in the wastewater community
and in the context of defining robust quality metrics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pitch presentation accepted for the 17th EPH Conference in Lisbon, 2024</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/news/2024-07-15-ephc-abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/news/2024-07-15-ephc-abstract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our abstract &amp;ldquo;High-resolution modeling and projection of heat-related mortality in Germany under climate change&amp;rdquo; got accepted for the upcoming European Public Health conference in Lisbon, taking place on November 13-15, 2024, in Lisbon, Portugal. Our paper will be presented as a pitch talk on Wednesday, November 13, 2024.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk Factors for Postoperative Delirium Severity After Deep Brain Stimulation Surgery in Parkinson&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/astalosch-2024-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/astalosch-2024-us/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the health effects of COVID-19-related immunisation disruptions in 112 countries during 2020-30: a modelling study</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/hartner-lancet-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/hartner-lancet-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linguistic markers of schizophrenia: a case study of Robert Walser</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/conference-paper/nenchev-etal-2024-linguistic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/conference-paper/nenchev-etal-2024-linguistic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 related disruption and resilience in immunisation activities in LMICs: a rapid review</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/hartnere-076607/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/hartnere-076607/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Objectives We conducted a rapid review to determine the extent that immunisation
services in low-income and middle-income countries (LMICs) were disrupted by the
COVID-19 pandemic and synthesised the factors that can be used to build resilience
in future.Design Rapid review reported in accordance with the Preferred reporting
for Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) guidelines.Data sources PubMed
and Web of Science were searched through 6 October 2023.Eligibility criteria for
selecting studies We included studies that focused on disruption to immunisation
activities due to the COVID-19 pandemic in LMICs. Outcomes included routine vaccine
coverage, supplementary immunisation activities, vaccine doses, timing of vaccination,
supply chain changes, and factors contributing to disruption or resilience.Data
extraction and synthesis Two independent reviewers used standardised methods to
search, screen and code studies. Quality assessment was performed using a modified
version of the Critical Appraisal Skills Programme for qualitative research. Findings
were summarised qualitatively.Results Of 4978 identified studies, 85 met the eligibility
criteria. Included studies showed declines in immunisation activities across LMICs
related to the COVID-19 pandemic. These included reductions in achieved routine
coverage, cancellation or postponement of campaigns and underimmunised cohorts.
Immunisation was most disrupted in the early months of the pandemic; however, recovery
varied by country, age-group and vaccine. Though many countries observed partial
recovery in 2020, disruption in many countries continued into 2021. It has also
been noted that clinician staff shortages and vaccine stock-outs caused by supply
chain disruptions contributed to immunisation delays, but that concern over COVID-19
transmission was a leading factor. Key resiliency factors included community outreach
and healthcare worker support.Conclusions There is limited information on whether
reductions in vaccination coverage or delays have persisted beyond 2021. Further
research is needed to assess ongoing disruptions and identify missed vaccine cohorts.All
data relevant to the study are included in the article or uploaded as supplementary
information.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Measure the Intelligence of Large Language Models?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/preprint/korber-2024-measureintelligencelargelanguage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/preprint/korber-2024-measureintelligencelargelanguage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the release of ChatGPT and other large language models (LLMs) the discussion about the intelligence, possibilities, and risks, of current and future models have seen large attention. This discussion included much debated scenarios about the imminent rise of so-called &amp;ldquo;super-human&amp;rdquo; AI, i.e., AI systems that are orders of magnitude smarter than humans. In the spirit of Alan Turing, there is no doubt that current state-of-the-art language models already pass his famous test. Moreover, current models outperform humans in several benchmark tests, so that publicly available LLMs have already become versatile companions that connect everyday life, industry and science. Despite their impressive capabilities, LLMs sometimes fail completely at tasks that are thought to be trivial for humans. In other cases, the trustworthiness of LLMs becomes much more elusive and difficult to evaluate. Taking the example of academia, language models are capable of writing convincing research articles on a given topic with only little input. Yet, the lack of trustworthiness in terms of factual consistency or the existence of persistent hallucinations in AI-generated text bodies has led to a range of restrictions for AI-based content in many scientific journals. In view of these observations, the question arises as to whether the same metrics that apply to human intelligence can also be applied to computational methods and has been discussed extensively. In fact, the choice of metrics has already been shown to dramatically influence assessments on potential intelligence emergence. Here, we argue that the intelligence of LLMs should not only be assessed by task-specific statistical metrics, but separately in terms of qualitative and quantitative measures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Past, present, and future heat-related mortality in Germany</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/preprint/wang-2024-past/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/preprint/wang-2024-past/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The role of the (in)accessibility of social media data for infodemic management: a public health perspective on the situation in the European Union in March 2024</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/10-3389-fpubh-2024-1378412/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/10-3389-fpubh-2024-1378412/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Public health institutions rely on the access to social media data to better understand the dynamics and impact of infodemics – an overabundance of information during a disease outbreak, potentially including mis-and disinformation. The scope of the COVID-19 infodemic has led to growing concern in the public health community. The spread of harmful information or information voids may negatively impact public health. In this context, social media are of particular relevance as an integral part of our society, where much information is consumed. In this perspective paper, we discuss the current state of (in)accessibility of social media data of the main platforms in the European Union. The European Union’s relatively new Digital Services Act introduces the obligation for platforms to provide data access to a wide range of researchers, likely including researchers at public health institutions without formal academic affiliation. We examined eight platforms (Facebook, Instagram, LinkedIn, Pinterest, Snapchat, TikTok, X, YouTube) affected by the new legislation in regard to data accessibility. We found that all platforms apart from TikTok offer data access through the Digital Services Act. Potentially, this presents a fundamentally new situation for research, as before the Digital Services Act, few platforms granted data access or only to very selective groups of researchers. The access regime under the Digital Services Act is, however, still evolving. Specifics such as the application procedure for researcher access are still being worked out and results can be expected in spring 2024. The impact of the Digital Services Act on research will therefore only become fully apparent in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating effective measles vaccine coverage in the Malaysian population accounting for between-dose correlation and vaccine efficacy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/shurendar-bmc-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/shurendar-bmc-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>German Text Embedding Clustering Benchmark</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/conference-paper/wehrli-etal-2023-german/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/conference-paper/wehrli-etal-2023-german/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This work introduces a benchmark assessing the performance of clustering German text embeddings in different domains. This benchmark is driven by the increasing use of clustering neural text embeddings in tasks that require the grouping of texts (such as topic modeling) and the need for German resources in existing benchmarks. We provide an initial analysis for a range of pre-trained mono- and multilingual models evaluated on the outcome of different clustering algorithms. Results include strong performing mono- and multilingual models. Reducing the dimensions of embeddings can further improve clustering. Additionally, we conduct experiments with continued pre-training for German BERT models to estimate the benefits of this additional training. Our experiments suggest that significant performance improvements are possible for short text. All code and datasets are publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Application areas of artificial intelligence in the context of One Health with a focus on antimicrobial resistance</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/pmid-37140603/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/pmid-37140603/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;strong&gt;full text&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;supplementary notes&lt;/strong&gt; for the publication here using Markdown formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Establishing Infodemic Management in Germany: A Framework for Social Listening and Integrated Analysis to Report Infodemic Insights at the National Public Health Institute</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/info-doi-10-2196-43646/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/journal-article/info-doi-10-2196-43646/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;: To respond to the need to establish infodemic management functions at the national public health institute in Germany (Robert Koch Institute, RKI), we explored and assessed available data sources, developed a social listening and integrated analysis framework, and defined when infodemic management functions should be activated during emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;: We aimed to establish a framework for social listening and integrated analysis for public health in the German context using international examples and technical guidance documents for infodemic management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;: This study completed the following objectives: identified (potentially) available data sources for social listening and integrated analysis; assessed these data sources for their suitability and usefulness for integrated analysis in addition to an assessment of their risk using the RKI&amp;rsquo;s standardized data protection requirements; developed a framework and workflow to combine social listening and integrated analysis to report back actionable infodemic insights for public health communications by the RKI and stakeholders; and defined criteria for activating integrated analysis structures in the context of a specific health event or health emergency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;: We included and classified 38{%} (16/42) of the identified and assessed data sources for social listening and integrated analysis at the RKI into 3 categories: social media and web-based listening data, RKI-specific data, and infodemic insights. Most data sources can be analyzed weekly to detect current trends and narratives and to inform a timely response by reporting insights that include a risk assessment and scalar judgments of different narratives and themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;: This study identified, assessed, and prioritized a wide range of data sources for social listening and integrated analysis to report actionable infodemic insights, ensuring a valuable first step in establishing and operationalizing infodemic management at the RKI. This case study also serves as a roadmap for others. Ultimately, once operational, these activities will inform better and targeted public health communication at the RKI and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
